this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio hello and welcome to software
engineering radio this is Travis Kimmel
today my guess is Kevin Goldsmith Kevin
is an experienced leader of high profile
high performing product research and
share technology engineering
organizations
until recently Kevin was the CTO at Avvo
the vice president of engineering
consumer and Spotify a director of
engineering at Adobe Systems and a
member of the Windows Media Windows CE
core OS and Microsoft Research teams at
Microsoft
Kevin thanks for joining Software
Engineering radio it's awesome to be
here very happy to join you today great
well today we're gonna be talking about
Conway's law how organizational design
influences architecture so we'll talk a
little bit about what that is and then
and then Kevin's experience with it so
why don't we start with just a quick
injury here what is Conway's law yeah so
Conway's law is interesting and it seems
to be having a new life in the industry
Conway Melvin Conway was was a software
architect back in the 60s and he wrote
this article for data Mason magazine in
April 1968 called how do committees
invent and it was more or less I like to
think about it you know having read it I
like to think about it as sort of the
equivalent
of a grumpy software developer blog post
of today we're really he was just
complaining that this pattern that he
saw in in his own teams that where the
software architectures he and his team
of architects were producing we're very
much mirroring the organizational
structures that they had that the way
the teams were laid out and he wrote
this article people thought about it a
little bit and then it kind of
disappeared and then every once in a
while including recently you start
hearing about it again as people are
starting to realize just that what he
hit on the absolute truth of this and it
became known as as Conway's off so what
what does this look like in your
experience what's a couple quick
examples we can dive in more in a bit
one of my favorite Restatement of
Conway's law so Conway's law as the way
it's traditionally stated is
organisations which design systems are
constrained to produce designs which are
copies of the communication structures
of these organizations pretty wordy not
necessarily clear my favorite
Restatement of it which also kind of
identifies this is from Eric Raymond he
says if you have four groups working on
a compiler you'll get a four pass
compiler right I love that yeah and it's
true like you know in your own teams you
can absolutely see this being the case
and and I did as well I you know and I
worked at you know I started working in
the industry back in the early 90s when
we were structuring things and very
traditionally very much actually not
that different from the way things were
structured in when Conway was was
working and you would see this very much
the way the team structured had a direct
correlation in to the architecture
because that's how you were splitting up
the work and it was it's a very natural
correspondence and and I saw this really
clearly when I was in much bigger teams
like at Microsoft where I sent where you
know as you decide when you make these
fundamental decisions okay which team is
going to own what or do
a new team we have this thing we want to
build do we need a new team for it what
would happen is you'd be just trying to
figure out how to split the work across
the people but you'd end up
inadvertently making important
architectural decisions that you'd end
up living with just because if a
different group of people builds a thing
they're gonna build it in a way that
makes sense to them and is independent
so that they can execute without being
stuck waiting for everybody else all the
time so it's I've just seen it over and
over again and then I've seen the
corollary as we become much more
cognizant of this factor changing how we
organize teams in order to take
advantage of it
so do you view this as something that is
really a law like is it inescapable or
are there are there notable counter
examples what are the boundaries of the
law so that's in that's a good question
because one of the things that you know
as I said like essentially this was
Conway kind of ranting and in a in a
very well-said way in a magazine because
he didn't have his own blog post back
then and it got called Conway's law but
it's not like physics but actually
people have tried to prove it it's come
out there's been a few different studies
notable one came from Harvard Business
School back in 2008 where they did this
study called exploring the duality
between product and organizational
architectures a test of the mirroring
hypothesis so another way that people
talk about Conway's law is this notion
of mirroring hypothesis that the
organizational structure mirrors the
software architectures are produced so
it's more of a business school case
study but they actually talk to lots of
different organizations and they found a
fairly good correspondence between this
they prove this mirroring hypothesis to
the extent that they could that yeah I
know there is this very strong
correspondence between this structure
and and and in the software architecture
so is it a law in like the speed of
light is a law or
you know you can't violate it no you you
can this is people this isn't laws of
physics this is psychology and sociology
and to a certain extent brain chemistry
which I can talk about but it's really
hard not to do it right so it isn't
impossible but it's you tend to go that
way whether you intend it whether you
mean to or not strong enough tendency
that we should pay attention you have
yeah if you don't pay attention it's
gonna happen it's absolutely gonna
happen and if you don't want it to
happen you have to work really hard to
make it not happen right so I'd love to
learn a little bit about your
experiences you know throughout your
career with this so you know what do
companies typically in some of the
places you've worked do they typically
approach this eyes open and design a an
org structure along the lines of the
architecture that they want a design or
is it something that's realized in the
retrospect I think there are companies
that have been very cognizant of this
force another way you talk about
Conway's law or the mirroring hypothesis
another way of staying is this
homomorphic force right it's which is a
mathematical concept but the idea that
there's a mirroring between between
these two things that are the similarly
structured desire to make these things
be the same so companies there have been
companies have been very cognizant of it
I either within the context of colonies
are just the this homomorphic forces
mirroring hypothesis companies like
Netflix companies like Amazon companies
like Spotify where I worked where they
deliberately structured their teams in a
way that reinforced yeah the
architectures that they wanted to build
or another way of saying it is they had
this structure that they wanted for
their teams that ended up producing the
optimal software structure that that has
supported them so when you think of all
these three companies you tend to think
about microservices right so there is
but all the all these companies have
structured themselves in a way that
only micro-service architectures really
work or SOA right because they have lots
of teams the teams are all working
independently of each other they talk to
each other through interfaces well the
only way to make that happen is for each
of these teams to own their own set of
independent services from each other
right if you can think about it
and I've definitely seen this a lot
especially talking to different startups
when you're a small company you're just
getting started you're a few developers
well what do you build you build a
monolith right one team a mano if is
easy to deploy a monolith is easy to
understand everybody can share the same
repo awesome you have one team one team
built one service your company if you're
coming successful it starts to grow well
now you need two teams right it's the
team has gotten too big well okay maybe
you can both work on the monolith but it
starts to become difficult just because
you have to coordinate stuff together
you know a great example actually of a
company that has figured out how to
build a monolith forever is Facebook
right but they're they have to deal a
lot to work around these issues with
Conway's law including just inventing
new computer science in order to make
some of their software architecture work
and support their model because it is so
distinct from their software
architecture but you know with a
start-up you're building your building
now you have two teams eventually that
frustration of both working on the
monolith maybe you figure out how to
split the monolith if you're lucky if
you're not you continue to work with it
and you you pay that down the road but
then you have three teams and you have
four teams and you have five teams and
what starts to happen is because your
software architecture and your
organizational structure are distinct
from each other there's a lot of tension
between them you broke the build and now
all of us can't work you know right
those kinds of things start to happen
which is why you tend to see as
companies grow and they start with the
monolith like everybody does you see all
these discussions all over the place of
how do we break up our monolith
how are we how are we doing that because
that it is so disjoint from their
organization that it becomes a problem
in itself so you said they structure the
team I'd love to pick it down a little
bit who care who inside the engineering
hierarchy does the structuring what role
is best suited to thinking about both
organizational structure and its impact
on architecture that's a great question
so I've seen this done in different ways
I think the the the way this works best
is more determined by the engineering
culture of the organization and less by
having a specific role so I have seen
companies have a software architecture
group successfully or a chief software
architect who would take on this
responsibility of deciding how systems
should be structured I've also seen this
and we did this a Tavo where there was a
more of a consensus driven approach for
well how do we as an organization think
we should do this and structures we put
structures in place to kind of make
those collective decisions efficiently I
think Spotify had achieve Software
Architect but his main role was more or
less making sure good good good
engineering principles were being used
in making decisions and asking
developers tough questions when they
wanted to diverge from things but though
those structures and architecture really
came very much from a individual team
and and sort of best practices coming
through the organization so and I've
seen it driven by somebody like me in
the CTO role as well I think it's really
going to determine be determined by the
company and in the structure how the
company wants to operate so if your CTO
and you're looking at making a bunch of
changes which are architectural you
suggest leading with with a team
structure or is it you know which comes
first
oh yeah okay I get to I get what you're
saying yeah so so there's two ways to do
this
would be to embrace Conway's law and say
well this is the team structure we have
so we should build a an architecture
that supports this because if we build
an architecture that doesn't map to our
team structure it's just gonna cause us
lots of challenges the other way to
approach it is to do what is called a
reverse Conway maneuver which is one of
my favorite phrases in the software
industry that is to say we want this
software architecture like pick the
software architecture first and then
design the team's so that they support
that software architecture so listen
give me an example of that how would
that actually work in practice
so Spotify is that okay so Spotify had a
SOA approach from the very beginning and
but it didn't start with the the team
structure that people associate with
Spotify it started with a much more
traditional kind of team structure and
so they have changed the for many
reasons but one of the reasons being
that they they were having this problem
of the software architecture and the
team architecture or the team design
being at odds with each other they
restructured teams in order to match the
software architecture they were trying
to drive and what happened as a result
depending on what you think of SOA or
microservices massive success or massive
failure I guess so you know Spotify had
when I left which was a couple years ago
stuff I had over 800 services in
production that's 800 different services
thousands of instances running but of
course but where the there was more than
one service per developer right now Wow
yes so when I left there's around I
think 800 developers around 800 services
but obviously 800 people in technology
right but that also included testers and
agile coaches and other folks as well so
if you want to I it worked incredibly
efficiently I mean Spotify is really
excellent I I think Netflix I
Netflix number is now but Netflix around
the same time had the same number of
services with fewer developers so how
does that matter how how is that an
instantiation of Conway's law is that is
that consistent yeah
so both Netflix and Amazon's the other
company I mentioned Netflix Spotify
Amazon they run their teams as
independent units right each of them is
kind of working on against its own set
of goals and operating fairly
autonomously I think Spotify by far the
most right that's the the kind of
critical part of Spotify is way of
working but certainly you know teams in
Netflix teams and Amazon function
independent of each other for the most
part so a non whether that needs to be
more than one service per team or not is
is questionable except for if like its
Spotify or Amazon a team gets too big
and you want to split it in half if that
team is building its own mini monolith
now you're stuck with restructuring that
monoliths just split it into two team to
split into pieces for each of the teams
if you start with these much smaller
building blocks tied to very specific
functionality if a team splits or team
divides up into 15 or whatever each of
those services can travel with the new
teams and so that gives you a lot more
flexibility where you're not having to
do this continual software we
architecture to make your software and
your team congruent so I guess I'm
having I'm having a bit of a hard time
envisioning what the organizational
structure of an 800 services micro
service team is is it fairly does that
mean that these things can the ownership
can be passed along in a fairly facile
way to teams own multiple services how
does that work what is a team so I know
best Spotify and and about UNIX elbow as
well although was also on this path but
not as far along so I can talk about it
at Spotify it's modified teams would own
many services sometimes on the order of
you know a couple dozen services for a
and what that meant was each of these
services would own a small piece of the
overall product there were a few large
services the playlist service at Spotify
is fairly massive but there were much
smaller services as well search suggests
was its own service so if you're typing
in the search bar and Spotify and you
get the list of suggestions that's an
independent service that runs into a
fairly small the beauty of these smaller
services would be that again like let's
say the playlist team decided to split
into two teams one just to do special
things for podcasts and the other one to
continue to focus on music the music
specific applications in that case
there's a some of these services are
already going to be structured towards
podcasts and those go with the podcasts
team and the other ones stay with the
music service so now one team instead of
owning 20 some or 30 some services now
one team owns twenty and one team owns
ten and so you can split them much
easier but also when if you wanted to
transition let's say because this did
happen while I was there the playlist
service was actually owned when I joined
by the infrastructure organization just
for whatever historical reason and they
were saying well we shouldn't be owning
the service a product team should own it
so they transitioned it over because the
service itself even though it's one of
the larger services is still a real
relatively small amount of functionality
relative to the entire product it was
able to be transitioned from team to
team from a completely different sets of
owners you know with a day or two of
like hand-holding and kind of walking
through the code because in itself was
relatively small so when services
transfer like that from from one team to
another is it typical for people to go
with them how's the domain knowledge
piece handled so I've done it different
ways in different organizations I think
that this one in this actually this
example I gave specifically is
interesting because it was transitioning
from a team
in Stockholm to a team in Gothenburg oh
wow sometimes you would do it with an
actual person moving from team to team
usually it'd be that be the case if that
person was particularly attached to
working on this problem they might
switch teams but often it wasn't that it
was no it was a handoff process where
there's sort of a sit-down a walk
through the service from the owning team
to the team that's taking it over to
make sure all the questions are asked
and you can talk through what we were
thinking we were gonna do this at some
point or this has been a challenge in
the past and you might want to look at
refactoring this you know basically do a
knowledge transfer and then pass that
you might have somebody kind of rotated
into a squad or a team for a couple
sprints kind of continuing their work
and before they go back to their team so
there's lots of different ways to do it
but essentially it's a like a normal
handoff process and sometimes it means a
person goes as well how important is the
notion of ownership let's sort of
functional ownership yeah with regard to
you organizational and architectural
design I mean it sounds like it's fairly
integral to a lot of what we've been
talking about it's a strong notion of
ownership but a key pieces so that's
actually a pretty that's actually a
really good question because I think we
didn't talk talk it all about functional
pressure in this case right so having
been in organisations where the
functional silos are distinct right at
Microsoft's back in the 90s when I was
there right you had product management
was this kind of own thing building the
specs handing him off to development or
we build them where we'd hand them off
to tasks to attest them right right and
so these functional silos tended these
created their own kind of Conway's law
problems just not because of the
software architecture but because of
this structural aspects of this where
you know the the spec was built
completely without technical problem
technical input but really driven
outside of the engineering team
and so the the product people would
build stuff that made sense from a user
perspective the program program managers
but made no sense from an engineering
perspective because of the way the
software was architected which would
require massive really textured
sometimes of components to make it work
in this way which would then delay the
release which would get it to testing
late which would require you know we're
a cross-functional team like a lot of
companies do now tends to not really
have that because everyone's part of
that decision-making process yeah but I
love it DeeDee
so do you I'm actually gonna follow up
on that one okay um I think there's a
difference between it almost sounds like
you're suggesting the difference between
micro service and a micro monolith I get
really I've gotten really careful about
the micro Service word partially because
I don't know if we all agree what that
is probably not what do you what do you
think a healthy definition of that is in
in this context I am scared to actually
say because I don't want to see what
people are gonna I don't want to hear
what people are gonna be yelling at
their phones when they hear me say it
but I think for me you know and that you
this is why I said well SOA or micro
service right right
one of the things based on your
definition whatever you all have in your
head is probably right what I'm gonna oh
the way I tend to think about it and
where I've seen it actually be very
valuable is a service that's small
enough that it's easier to rewrite than
it is to refactor I love that if you
think about it and there's it's there's
a lot of overhead involved right if that
would mean you have lots of services
right which means you have to have a
infrastructure that supports having lots
of services I think when we tell when we
were really talking about micro servers
a lot was before service right service
now is essentially kind of micro
services taken to the extreme or taken
to its next logical step but what I
liked about the way we would structure
services at Spotify was that
you know the problems I'd seen when
we're building larger services of we
have a new API version so now we have a
bunch of stuff in the code well if
you're using this version of the API
we're gonna do this if you're using this
version the API we're gonna do this
slightly differently and it becomes a
little bit of a business logic rat's
nest sometimes in the code supporting
all these different API endpoints and
instead what you could do is say no
there's gonna be like we wrote this
service to support version 6
well now we're doing version 7 we're
just gonna write a new service because
it it's small enough that that is a
matter of a Sprint versus six months
right we do that and the the logic now
is very dedicated we are saw we are
doing this in the way this version of
the API works we have clients continuing
to talk to the old version of the API we
can actually watch that right so in a
company like Spotify where you have
external API folks Hardware talking to
specific versions of API things like
that you really can't retire old api's
ever but you can watch usage right so
how many times is this is version six of
this API being hit and there's a
threshold below which you can say okay
well now we can finally retire this and
just shut the service down that
implementations service version seven is
still running so you had a service
talking to both endpoints and you've got
all this code in that service to support
the different or however this is
slightly different from each other when
you kit when you can say well we can
turn off version six well you still have
all this code still that you're either
gonna have to refactor or just live with
this kind of crufty dead code and you're
in your code which produces bugs which
produces quality issues which may
produce scaling issues so being able to
say now we're just gonna have a new
service here rather than continue to
work on an existing service is really
powerful it's also easier to test
there's a there's a lot of benefit to
that so that's what I think I might
think of when I think of micro services
awesome so do you see Conway's law
playing out with
cross-functional teams I mean crush
front it seems to be one of the main
trends in the industry right now yes
ight this notion of cross-functional
teams do you see that playing out with
regard to Conway's law and and if so how
there's a part and when I think of teams
you know one of the things I like to
think of and this shows well not just my
Spotify kind of bias but but also some
of the things that I was working on
before and since what I think of when I
think of effective teams is I think of
teams that are working on sort of their
different components that are able to
work independently of each other and
that to me is a highly desirable thing
for a software engineering organization
is that the teams don't have a lot of
strict dependencies between them because
that tends to slow them down so where
that Maps very well - Conway's law if
these teams are independent and they
each own ed by design or by organic
these teams each own their own modules
that builds the software architecture
that's great cross-functional howdy
comes into it back more to the idea that
these teams can operate independently of
each other and so a cross-functional
team has much fewer dependencies onto
centralized organizations so when I
build teams I like to have if I can
designer if the team owns UI I want to
have a designer who sits in the team
that that means is because I've been in
organizations where design was
centralized and you know if we needed
some help with some UI I had to sort of
fill out my requests and paper and
triplicate to a sort of centralized
design organization and so that they
could give me four weeks or four hours
of a designers time nine days in the
future right and so having that
cross-functional team means that that
team can operate independently and
doesn't have to wait for things which I
like and whoa what size do you see
companies sort of hitting that threshold
I mean all companies are sort of born
tiny and modeling right and then oh boy
is it
is it's time to start thinking about you
know either breaking that up or doubling
down you know where's that where does
the pain start to hit and what does that
feel like well I think that it's gonna
depend a lot on your your budget and
your ability to hire and a lot of things
right so in a company with a the ability
to hire fairly well and the budget to be
able to staff up it's fairly easy to
build these kind of independent
autonomous teams that are fully
cross-functional right
Spotify is a great example a lot of
companies don't have that and it just
really like that's life right like you'd
you have enough budget for three
designers but you have six teams so in
that world you're gonna have to figure
out a different structure but still you
can do this in an acknowledgement of
looking for where the bottlenecks are
and then just trying to get rid of them
so I think that you know one thing I
like to think about when I think about
this because when you think
cross-functionally and when we think
about software teams we tend to think
you know you might think like front-end
dev and or full stack dev and back-end
dev or maybe data or design tests all
those different kind of traditional
functions but data is a new one right
right and data engineering and data
science was so rare and so hard to find
those people that you are only going to
be able to have one or two for your
organization right so then you couldn't
distribute them you couldn't have truly
cross-functional team but you would
might start with that where you're you
know they're picking the they're on the
projects that are most critical or
they're going team to team and helping
where they can as you as an organization
get better at utilizing those folks you
hiring more and eventually you reach a
sort of critical mass where you no
longer need to centralize it you can now
distribute that function which brings
that knowledge just like we did with
tests just like we did with products or
program management that got distributed
and
value to the team was having these
different functional voices represented
was pretty pretty significant right how
things worked before and after so I
think that's the way I like to think
about like any new function and how to
distribute it you have to start from a
centralized kind of timeshare model
until you develop that critical mass
where you can distribute it but that
should always be your goal yeah that
should always be the endgame
yeah and I'm fairly opinionated you can
hear about software architecture in the
way that I wanna the way that I like to
see it structured in the way that I've
seen it work well you can apply these I
be the same ideas are always gonna be
there no matter what your preferred
software architecture and I think the
the critical piece there is just
understanding that and and taking
advantage of that or just working with
that understanding so it sounds like the
suggestion here is that almost like a
temporary embed is better and sort of
more in line with Conway's law than
these fractionally units of someone's
time like a half day here six hours here
oh yeah is that fair
yeah yeah I don't know if Melvin Conway
would say that but that's what I'm gonna
say that's what I'm gonna say for him I
think that but that's also just for me
level of efficiency right so if you need
you know if you're working on something
and that something requires a skill set
and that skill set is distant from you
in the organization it's very hard to
get any kind of quick response right if
I have to you know apply for a data
scientists time to help with this
problem and that person isn't available
to me because they're working on
something else for a week I'm now stuck
for a week if that person instead spends
two weeks sitting with me in my team
where we can have very good interaction
and I can ask all my questions as I come
up with them I'm gonna have a lot better
context where I may not need as much of
their time right do you see any sort of
common Conway's law anti patterns that
are recurring in the industry oh that's
a good question I haven't thought about
that I'm trying to think where people
are just like doing something really
dumb
or things where you come in and you're
like well that is a classic Conway's law
style problem right you have oh yeah one
of the things I haven't seen this quiet
as much I still see it some from time to
time right is these teams and and by the
way like this is how I structured my
organization at Adobe where one thing I
see is a pretty common pattern is this
thing where okay well we have the server
team then we have the client team then
we have like the core library team and
these are all separate teams and then
people will come to me and say hey Kevin
like can you do a call with us and help
us with some challenges we're having in
the organization okay yeah what's going
on well everything's taking so long
because every new feature comes from the
client team and then they have to
request the functionality from the Kuril
a great team which has to request the
functionality from the server team and
this organizational structure is very
much mapping onto the layer cake of our
architecture but what that actually the
value that brings or the that's just
slowing all product development down
because we're having to coordinate
across these different silos that's a
that's a sort of very classic example
and it that is how we structure teams
for longest time you put all the server
developers together you put all the the
court you know that's the piece that
talks to the server and supports the
functionality to the different clients
and then the client teams that was a
very obvious way to structure your
organization but it was an obvious way
to structure your organization because
that was how you divided the work on the
architecture this is another case we're
moving from a monolith approach to an
SOA approach let's you actually say well
no like the the services that support
this set of functionality is going to
live in the team that owns the front end
right so that we can this is where we
get into the full stack developers and
the full steams that completely own the
feature team model is sort of a solution
for that anti-pattern but that it that
pattern being an anti-pattern is
relatively new right I love you brought
the full stack developer do you when
you're putting together these
cross-functional teams is that a skill
set that you look for or you know is it
more like a myth the people that they
want to sort of you know vertical
feature ownership what's your view on
that so you know I've worked with a lot
of skilled full-stack developers I tend
to think and maybe this is my own bias
as a developer or having been a
developer for a number of years right I
think that we all can do lots of stuff
because we're interested in lots of
things and we can learn lots of
different skills but I do think that we
all naturally have an affinity towards
one side or the other I don't think
anybody's a pure full stack developer
that's amazing at building services and
also amazing at crafting you know user
interface I think you tend to have a
proclivity on one side or the other and
so just acknowledging that like there's
folks who do full stack and there they
love building the backend but only so
they can make a better front-end and
then folks who love full stack because
they love building the backend and they
can do the front-end to if they need to
and so building when you build a team
like I'll build a I like building with
full stack devs but I'll mix it up like
you people will tell you like well I
like both but I can do both I prefer one
or the other and then try and match them
up it's this idea that the t-shaped
person like I can do machine learning
and like simple machine learning and I
can also do iOS development and I can
also do this but I'm a I'm a real expert
at writing efficient database code right
that's that's my depth right and then
mixing that all up in a team so you get
a nice breadth and depth is is a good
skill to have or a good way to produce
good teams so with the onset of a new
software project is it from your view is
it sort of inevitable that it started as
a monolith it isn't inevitable it's just
natural so
right you can either choose to do that
or choose not to do that I think when
you're building a new product and maybe
it's different now I think one things I
tend to see this a lot in these
companies that are kind of going through
this you know this now somewhat classic
monolith to micro-services transition is
these are all companies of a certain age
primarily who sort of came of age in the
days before public cloud when you were
still racking your own servers and you
know you're and and so in that world
like having a deployment that is you
know SCP of a single service that's
pretty awesome and saves you a lot of
time at the beginning nowadays you know
companies forming now they're they're
much more quick to embrace that sort of
smaller service approach because they
can leverage all the infrastructure that
the public clouds give them and they
don't have to build as much of a
capability around because there's a lot
of infrastructure support you need right
so now between you know docker and
kubernetes and just serverless
in those kind of pieces and cloud
formation or whatever it's much much
easier to build a micro service
architecture or a SOA architecture from
the beginning than it used to be so I
don't know if it's just because I tend
to talk to a lot of companies in that 10
you know that 8 to 10 year 8 to 12 year
range who started with a monolith
because they were running out of their
own Colo and buying machines and this
was the easiest way to do it
I don't see that as much anymore so for
teams that are that are in that
transition from a big monolith to to
micro services or they're they're
breaking up the app in some fashion how
do you go about maintaining
architectural integrity of the product
as teams be you know as soon as we come
larger and then split right and the
architecture splits yeah I mean if I
could solve that problem in a sentence I
should you know I should write a book
and solve this problem this is such I
mean there are so many company
struggling with this including you know
you know when I came to Avago was
in the head started this transition and
was struggling with it just like
everybody else and I would love to say
to people listening oh well all we did
was this and we totally solved it but no
we struck we continued to struggle with
it the whole time I was there we made a
lot of progress but you know it's it's a
challenge I think the pattern there's a
few patterns I've seen that I find
really interesting one was the one I
heard about that they did at Warby
Parker where rather than sort of start
splitting individual pieces of
functionality out into their own
services instead what they did is split
their monolith into four smaller
monoliths and then split each of those
monoliths and just for smaller monoliths
as a different way of approaching the
problem and just finding those cut lines
was critical obviously but that led them
tease it apart I think you know in a
more ease in an easier fashion but that
doesn't work in correspondence with
Conway's law necessarily how do you know
if you're dividing things up into
monoliths versus versus microservices I
mean I know it sounds like a silly
question but yeah there's so much
difference in how we use terms in the
industry and that's why I I mean I'm
trying to be really careful how I use it
workers what I would say again like one
of the things the way we approached it
was I would the approach I think a lot
of companies do which was we found
individual pieces of functionality in
our monolith so a single api's right
here's an API that returns returns this
set of information about an attorney
okay on the monolith okay so what we can
do is let's put a new API a new service
that just calls through to the monolith
and then we will extract all the logic
out of the monolith and put it into this
service and then it stops calling the
monolith and this functionality is
removed from the mouth that's running in
its own service to the extent that again
like the way I think of micro services
is it's easier to rewrite and write a
new one than refactor that tended to be
fairly small and when I say rewrite it's
you know a
branch right to rewrite that certainly
you go where we were at with a lot of
services that Spotify and when we
started by the time we were done or by
the time we I left the ah that's kind of
where we were now - it was much easier
to write a new service and it was to add
functionality to the monolith and that
let us pull stuff out of the monolith on
on a much better basis so small small
enough so as the code breaks apart a
little bit who helps manage the
communication between dependencies that
might still exist there so one of the
things I like with the right kind of
developer culture you have in your teams
for it works pretty well when multiple
teams are all kind of working together
on a monolith there has to be some level
of communication they can all be working
on their own things but in the end this
thing is gonna get deployed as a unit
and when it gives when it goes down
somebody's gonna get called and they're
gonna have to respond and it's not gonna
be obvious whose code broke right so you
have to share knowledge across that team
it doesn't change that much when you're
doing this transition right so a team
will say like hey we're gonna pull this
code out of the monolith like this is
kind of functionality that maps to what
our team does we're gonna move this out
into its own service and just making the
rest of the folks working on the
monolith aware of that usually you might
actually have if other teams like have
some sort of visibility into that part
of the code having them do code reviews
but generally making sure there's
there's just people are aware of what's
going on I think part of this as well is
being careful about overstating code
ownership so right if you say well I own
this code or my team owns this code you
put yourself but other people have
dependencies on this code you put
yourself in a situation where if team B
needs something in a service that's
maintained by team a and they're not
they have to make a request to Team A
which has to be
our ties against whatever else team a is
doing which means team B is now waiting
for who knows how long I've seen that a
lot I don't like that so instead I like
to say you know if team B needs
something in a service that's nominally
like team a is operationally responsible
for Team B let's team a no hey we're
gonna make this change just in case team
a says well hey we were just about to
get rid of that service or something
just so you don't have miscommunications
their team a says okay you go ahead and
make your change team B makes a change
in team a's code team a code reviews a
change accepts it and then deploys it
and that way you know they're that
operational responsibility peace peace
is pretty key because again somebody's
getting oaken up when something doesn't
work but i don't like have having teams
have to be dependent on each other for
changes to code so I'd rather have each
two everybody cone code is owned by
everybody but operational responsibility
is clearly delineated as well as a way
and that which requires pretty
significant communication right it
sounds like it borrows a little bit from
some I mean open source practices right
you're welcome to come change it but
we're gonna review it and make sure it
passes yes it's where the owners of the
project know it's I mean that's exactly
where I'm inspired by yeah it's just how
open-source projects work and as most of
that style communication typically done
ad hoc I mean in places you've worked
yeah well not necessarily places I've
worked but in places that I've had the
ability to influence and or change how
it works yeah it is so having worked in
very structured kind of environments
where communication flows only through
very specific channels very sort of like
that the places that are not that
distinct from where Conway was working I
always bristled at that because you you
you know the communication between teams
was really tightly controlled and
structured and it removed a lot of the
important kind of co-ownership of things
and so in organizations where I've been
able to influence
and or direct how things should work
yeah I prefer this developer to
developer kind of more ad hoc
communication in the channel for that
communication is typically pull requests
or what are the mechanics buying that so
it can be any number of things it can be
pull requests it can be slack channels
it can be you know Spotify had has this
notion of guilds where folks who work
across in a skill set will meet together
across all the different teams on a
regular basis to discuss best practices
or or challenges they're saying we had a
Tavo we had a weekly meeting for all
which ever developers wanted to show up
an open invite meeting to talk about
what we called strategy tech strategy
where people could say hey I'm thinking
I've got this problem I'm thinking about
solving it this way what does everybody
else think that ended up being a good
way to share kind of developer to
developer and and raise issues that
maybe one developer was seeing on
another team that another developer on a
different team had are just solved right
there's also you know in matrix
organizations like Spotify like Alvo
became you also have that sort of your
immediate peers in your in the
management structure who span multiple
groups and can share information that
way as well and are those so setting up
and establishing those communication
structures when they may not exist is
that just sort of something that you do
by Fiat how does that come to be there's
a combination of sort of nudging I like
to manage by nudging primarily the less
by Fiat because my Fiat tends to mean
that you know people tend to resent
somebody who just says do it this way
because I want you to do it this way so
instead I kind of managed a lot more
through kind of nudging like hey maybe
we should have something like this or
maybe this might work and then try and
get somebody excited about it and have
them kind of take it and drive it
themselves I mean if I can get somebody
excited about it I think these kind of
ad-hoc communication structures work
much better if it is not something that
management imposes but something
actually
the developers build themselves and
maintain themselves so that the meaning
that I mention in Abba that was started
by one of the developers and run by the
developers themselves I would come I
would sometimes speak if I had an
opinion but it wasn't my meeting right
so I was just there to participate and
that meant that you know they they could
raise the issues that they had as
opposed to me setting an agenda and so
you or I definitely see this I mean
slacks the great equalizer right and in
slacks and really great for this or IRC
channels before it it's essentially
taking those things where people already
self-organized and just making it and
giving it more support for to take that
beyond the virtual so one of the things
I always find fasting about Conway's
laws it's specifically about the
communication structure right which of
course follows a word structure and all
that do you do you think there's so
placed for sort of regular formal
meetings and how do you approach that
kind of thing um yeah I think I always
tend to think of things in terms of
communication pathways within an
organization so because that is really
how that tends to influence beyond
software architecture influences a lot
who talks to who and how thing how
information moves through an
organization makes it shows a lot about
how that organization gets its work done
and that and software architecture just
being one part of it and so in an
organization I lead like sure you're
still gonna have these kind of formal
meetings some of which are going to be
me communicating to my team because I
have access you know spreading the
knowledge that I have about what's going
on to them I think that's still valuable
but I also try and encourage these
person-to-person kind of informal
meetings or formal as well one-on-ones
peer-to-peer one-on-ones peer-to-peer
mentoring team meetings these kind of
community of interest meetings just as a
way of trying to break through the
different silos that you have right so
Conway was really reacting to how the
silos of the organization produced
sometimes inferior software
architectures but they were mapped to
those silos so I like breaking apart
finding ways to kind of subvert the
silos Asian as much as possible so even
in a company like Spotify where you tend
to think of it as this really autonomous
and like all this great stuff
there's absolutely communication flows
and networks and those are influencing
the structure influencing lots of
different things and so that's why you
have these elements like guilds because
the tribes at Spotify the squads were
their own silos and they weren't
functional silos they were sort of
feature silos and then the tribes were
silos and this is where those guilds
could kind of break through those things
and finding other conduits like the
Spotify has a strong agile coach
population and they become their own
kind of functional network that
transcends all the different silos and
so as a leader you learn how to take
advantage of these different networks to
spread information but also to glean
information yeah I don't know if I just
answered your question you said you like
to encourage these kind of alternate
communication channels what is one of
the mechanics by that it's sort of like
the inverse not right but what does that
kind of support look like is it's
sponsoring lunch I mean you're just
bolts yeah yeah I mean you know
certainly it's stuff like that it's it's
it's encouraging people who-who will
come to you and say hey I'd like to do a
lunch and learn on this like yeah
absolutely I'll pay for a lunch go for
it it's setting up meetings so one thing
I did whoa
based on my experiences other places was
a kind of a yearly mini developer
conference I did one for data and then
one for product development where
everybody could just it was open
invitation it was day there's food it
was an unconference style so it wasn't
you know me driving an agenda but was an
opportunity this for people to speak to
each other and start
build correspondences and that works
sort of more organically rather than
start creating it so finding
opportunities to bring folks from
different teams together and get them
find ways to get them speaking to each
other would tend to build these networks
in a very kind of organic and loose way
but we also did things at a table like
build a mentoring Network a very
explicit sign up for a meant to either
to mentor well you had to both mentor
and if you wanted to be mentor so is a
two-way thing that helped build
correspondences you can also do this
really effectively if you're if you have
an organization that's more self
organized so there's a company in
Seattle called qo who builds storage
appliances for enterprises and they do
periodic restructuring exercise where
it's essentially like a job fair and
everybody can join switch teams and that
tends to produce organization where your
network spans lots of different teams
within the company another thing that
companies do and was really valuable
I first did it Spotify it would be these
kind of onboarding teams where you join
the team I know lots of companies do
this we join the team when you start and
you work on that team for you know a
couple weeks or a month or something
with people who are moving on to all
different teams and that kind of
kickstart to network for you within the
company where you know people in lots of
different parts of the organizations
that as another way of kind of breaking
through Silas so how do you know if it's
time to really focus on this in a
meaningful way
I mean what's what are the signs that
you may have a communication bottleneck
so I think you know one of the things I
will do periodically and well I hear
this a lot let me step back I hear this
a lot from companies where you know
they'll call me and they'll say like hey
can you dial into this meeting you know
we've been really structure we've been
really challenged by our ability to
execute like we're moving way too slow
right like here's so often like we're
moving way too
so and we don't understand why and
things are should be going a lot faster
and one of the things I'll say around
that is like you know how are you
actually mapping how stuff moves through
the organization that some exercises
I've done within my own organization
like when you feel like something should
be going faster than it is and and there
are tools that let you measure things
but I tend to go by you know how is it
actually feeling right you do an
exercise where like you spend a couple
weeks and you track work through the
through your teams so you know we're
building this new feature okay oh this
team needed to do this and then it goes
to this team and this could even be
within a single team but it's going from
this person this person that waited you
know just a total Kanban kind of view to
track work through it and if you do that
for a few weeks you'll start to see
patterns oh well
everything seems to get stuck here
things get stuck other places but this
seems to be the primary bottleneck and
that's an opportunity to look at it and
go okay well is this team understaffed
is this team like does this team need to
be a separate team like that's where you
can start looking for options but
without if you just ask people why is
stuff slow they'll all tell you
different things and because none of
them have that complete picture of how
work moves through so each person in the
organization is going to identify
different areas to what they think the
problem is but they don't have the
broader view so actually mapping out how
the work moves through the organization
actually tracking individual pieces of
work and finding where they get stuck
that gives you a lot better insight I
love that alright well is there anything
we haven't discussed yet that we should
have oh I think we've got to talk about
you know one of my favorite parts when I
when I think about Conway's law is how
it actually Maps your brain ooh I love
it which I didn't get to talk about I
want to talk about that yeah
so one of the things is kind of
interesting and as I was you know I
originally gave a talk at the software
architecture called the o'reilly
software architecture conference a while
ago specifically about this
correspondence between software
architecture and organizational design
and as part of this and just kind of
doing more research and trying to learn
more about it so that could you know
speak about it
I talked to Brent and Riata who is a
sort of organizational sociologist but
also has done a lot working at brain and
how your brain responds to different
inputs from the organization and I was
explaining to her what Conway's law was
and and some of the things that I'd seen
and she actually brought up an important
thing that I had never really thought
about and then I studied a little bit
more and was really fascinated by
there's a part of your brain in the
hippocampus called the internal complex
that part of your brain has is where you
store all your maps so it's your
physical maps it's like how you know to
get from your house to the bus and the
bus to the office right and you can kind
of do that on an autopilot after the
first couple times because that map is
stored in your brain but that also tends
to contain the maps of the social
structures that you operate in within as
well and so like your organizational
structure in the company you work for is
also stored in that internal complex and
the software architecture that you work
on that is very much a map right and
your end and this homomorphic force I
mentioned before this mathematical thing
the mirroring hypothesis Conway's law
essentially what's a saying is you have
this strong force that wants to wants
these two different graphs let's say to
be similar where they it because that
makes mapping easier so you can think
about this in this context you're
working on a software project let's say
you're in a more traditional structure
you work on
back and you're a user of your product
and you see a bug in the android client
and you want to say oh i should tell the
that team that i found this bug i should
i should i should give them the bug and
then you have to think about well who's
on that team like who do I send the bug
to and the fact is like okay well you
have this software architecture because
you know the software architecture in
your head
if the organizational structure maps to
that software architecture clearly you
go oh I send it to the Android team
that's pretty obvious if for example
your software architecture and your
organizational architecture are distinct
like the android client is actually
owned by the hana web team and you go i
don't wait you actually don't know like
well i know there's an android client
but there's no team that maps to this
which team owns us and you know like
it's a perennial problem like who's
supposed to get this bug i don't know
who owns this thing so this is one of
these cases where this homomorphic force
this interview you know where your to
maps want to be similar in your internal
complex this actually leads you back
into Conway's law and it makes things a
lot easier
so this is one of these cases where you
know you asked is it a law and the
answer is no of course that's not a law
it's like there's no no one's going to
arrest you for building a software
architecture that is not congruent with
your organizational design however if
you choose to ignore it and build these
two things in very different ways
nobody's gonna have any clue who to talk
to or who's responsible for anything and
there's gonna be continual pressure to
make these things make be the same
because your internal Maps don't match
up at all and it's you're literally
fighting your own brain here and
actually having kind of come to that
realization started to make me
understand because why this actually was
such a problem to try and avoid Conway's
law or subvert Conway's law your brain
is actually going to fight you on that
one
yeah you're referencing the same
exactly and we're when they're different
Maps like you can't map between them
there's no there's no linear mapping
from component to component and it
really confuses you and makes it very
hard for you to to do your job I love
that all right well I think that's a
wrap
thanks for joining us today Kevin's
Travis Kimmel for software engineering
radio and we'll see you next time thanks
for listening to se Radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening